<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Theorems evincing, that the subject of the fourth and fifth chapters of the Revelation, is the Church of England, B.L.E. With answers to objections. Humbly offered to the serious consideration of all enemies of the Church of England, dissenters and separatists. By Wal. Garrett, rector of Everly in Wiltshire: sometime fellow of Trinity College in Cambridge.</title>
            <author>Garrett, Walter.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 23 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A42415</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G271C</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R218820</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99830377</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99830377</idno>
            <idno type="VID">34828</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A42415)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 34828)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2091:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Theorems evincing, that the subject of the fourth and fifth chapters of the Revelation, is the Church of England, B.L.E. With answers to objections. Humbly offered to the serious consideration of all enemies of the Church of England, dissenters and separatists. By Wal. Garrett, rector of Everly in Wiltshire: sometime fellow of Trinity College in Cambridge.</title>
                  <author>Garrett, Walter.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>9, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed and are to be sold by the booksellers of London and Westminster,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1700?]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon; date of publication conjectured by Wing.</note>
                  <note>In two columns.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in St. David's University College Library, Lampeter, Wales.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Revelation, IV-V --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:34828:1"/>
            <head>THEOREMS; Evincing, That the Subject of the Fourth and Fifth Chapters of the <hi>REVELATI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ON,</hi> is the Church of <hi>ENGLAND,</hi> B. L. E. With ANSWERS to OBJECTIONS.</head>
            <head type="sub">Humbly offered to the Serious Conſideration of All ENE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MIES of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> DISSEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TERS and SEPARATISTS. By <hi>Wal. Garrett,</hi> Rector of <hi>Everly</hi> in <hi>Wiltſhire:</hi> Sometime Fellow of Trinity College in <hi>Cambridge.</hi>
            </head>
            <q>
               <p>Who hath Believed our Report, and to whom is the Arm of the Lord Revealed?</p> 
               <bibl>Eſai. liii. 1.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>The Harveſt is Plenteous, but the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers are Few,</p> 
               <bibl>Mat. ix. 37.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>I Have Already (by God's Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance) Giv'n-forth an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of Every Particular, in the Fourth and Fifth Chapters of the Revelation; and now come to Evince the CERTAINTY of it: by laying down ſuch Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rems, or Propoſitions, of Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionable Verity, as will ſerve at Once both to Eſtabliſh my own Expoſition, and to Refell All O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Whatſoever.</p>
            <p n="1">(I.) The Church Deſcrib'd in <hi>Rev.</hi> iv, and v. was not in Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, when St. <hi>John</hi> Receiv'd the Viſion. For the Viſion is Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Entitl'd by the Spirit Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, Chap. iv. 1. <hi>Things that muſt be HERE AFTER.</hi> (II.) The Throne in thoſe Chapters therefore, is not the Throne of God, in the Higheſt Heav'n; nor the Sitter on the Throne, God Almighty Himſelf in Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; (for Theſe were not Things to Come, but have been the SAME from All Eternity:) but the Sitter on the Throne, is God Ruling in and by ſome Earthly Potentate; and his Throne is a Throne on EARTH. And Conſequently, The Church in which this Throne is Set, and over which the Sitter on it does
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:34828:2"/>Preſide, is a Church on Earth. (III.) Whereas they are ſaid, <hi>Not to Reſt Day and Night, ſaying, Holy, Holy, Holy, Lord God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty; Which Was, and Is, and is to Come:</hi> It cannot hence be Concluded, That they ſhould Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver take any Reſt in Sleep; nor that Always, when Awake, they ſhould be ſaying, Holy, Holy, Holy, &amp;c. but that they ſhould Say it Every Day, and Every Night; or Every Morning, and Every Ev'ning; and That, Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten at Every Time; and very Obſervably; or to Some Such Senſe, as That is. As, when S. <hi>Paul</hi> enjoyns Every Chriſtian, <hi>to Pray without Ceaſing,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> v. 17. So, <hi>Eph.</hi> vi. 8. <hi>Act.</hi> xx. 31. <hi>Rom.</hi> i. 9. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> i. 3. For it is a very Common Phraſe; and Can Mean no other, but Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly, at certain Returns of Time; or ſome Such Thing. (IV.) Neither ought it hence to be Inferr'd, That this Church was to make uſe of No Other Words, in her Addreſſes, but <hi>Holy, H, H; L, G, A,</hi> &amp;c. But only, That ſhe was to Uſe a Conſtant FORM, of Prayer and Praiſe; in which, One of the moſt Remarkable Things ſhould be, her Glorifying the Bleſſed Trinity Only. For that this Church is here ſet forth, as Uſing a FORM, is Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniable. And therefore No Church that does not uſe a Form, of Glorifying the Bleſſed Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; (Nay, that does not uſe it Much, and very Obſervably,) can be the Church here Deſcrib'd. For, How Odly would it look, to pretend to Give an Idea, of a Church that is a Profeſt Enemy of Forms; or that hardly Ever Mentions the Trinity Diſtinctly in their Prayers, by telling us, That <hi>they Reſt not Day, and Night, Saying, Holy, Holy, Holy, Lord God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, which Was, and Is, and is to come?</hi> As on the Other ſide, it is the Very Characteriſtic of Our Church's Service. Inſomuch that I cannot Forbear to ſay, That to him that is in Search, after the Church here Prefigur'd, That One Circumſtance is Sufficient to Fore-ſtall his Judgment for the Church of <hi>England.</hi> (V.) There is No Neceſſity, That they ſhould uſe Thoſe Very Words neither; It is Enough, if the Words be LIKE them. For Identity is not Requir'd in Viſions, but Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs Only. Thus a City, in Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy is call'd a Woman; a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, a Beaſt; <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Becauſe of their Near Reſemblance, as to thoſe Things the Prophecy Reſpects in them; as, the Parturiency of the One, and the Savageneſs of the Other. It is therefore, for the Fulfilling of the Prophecy we are Speaking of, Sufficient, if the Church gives Glory to the Bleſſed Trinity in Words LIKE Theſe, <hi>Holy, H, H; L, G, A: Which Was, and Is, and is to Come;</hi> Such, for Example, as
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:34828:2"/>are Theſe of Our Church, <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry be to the Father, and to the Son, and to the Holy Ghoſt; As it Was in the Beginning, Is Now, and Ever ſhall be, World without end.</hi> Where we ſee the Words <hi>[As it Was, Is now, and ever ſhall be,]</hi> Perfectly to Correſpond to Thoſe in the Type, <hi>[Which Was, and Is, and is to Come.]</hi> And (in the Former Clauſe) <hi>Father, Son, and H. Ghoſt,</hi> Anſwer as Directly to <hi>Lord, God, Almighty;</hi> and <hi>Glory,</hi> to <hi>Holineſs.</hi> For God is ſaid to be <hi>Glorious in Holineſs, Exod.</hi> xv. 11. For as the Uſual Notion of Holineſs in Scripture, is Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration: So the Glory of God is, that Nothing can be <hi>Compar'd to him, Eſai.</hi> xl. 18. xlvi. 5. (VI.) The Sealed Book is That, whoſe Viſions are Diſtinctly Set-down, in the Sixth, and Following Chapp. This is Plain to Senſe (VII.) By Op'ning the SEALS of this Book, is Meant Explaining it. There is No Other Senſe of Op'<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the <hi>Seals</hi> of Any Book, throughout the Scripture. For Sealing Always ſingnifies Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealing the Senſe of a Myſtery; and Op'ning is Explaining it. For which, ſee <hi>Dan.</hi> ix. 24. and xii. 4. <hi>Eſai.</hi> xxix. 11. <hi>Luk.</hi> xxiv. 32. <hi>Acts</hi> xvii. 3. And I am very well Aſſur'd, there is No One Place to the Contrary. I do not ſay, That Barely to O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p'n a Book, is to Explain it: but to Op'n the SEALS of a Book; or to Op'n the Text, or Writing, of a Book: for the Seals are Always upon the Text; and Not upon the Cover, Paper, or Parchment of a Book. And if the Book we are ſpeaking of, had been Sealed only with Wax, Lead, or Ir'n, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> What Need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed All That Ceremony, (Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth ſo Particularly, and Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pouſly, in the vth. Chapter) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Looſing of its Seals, when Every Mechanic could have done it? But it is There Affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, That <hi>No one in Heav'n, nor in Earth, nor <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder the Earth, could do it.</hi> What? Not Break, or File, or Cut, or ſome way or other Get-off, a Seal from a piece of Parchment? That's ſtrange indeed! (VIII.) It is not God's Giving his Son the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, that is Deſcrib'd in <hi>Rev.</hi> v. For That was Done <hi>Before</hi> the Viſion was Exhibited to S. <hi>John.</hi> But the Viſion of <hi>Rev.</hi> v. is Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly a Part of thoſe things, which the Spirit Entitles, <hi>Things that were to come to paſs AFTER</hi> Chap. iv. 1. (IX.) The Viſion therefore of <hi>Rev.</hi> v. is a Prefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guration of the Circumſtances, that were to Accompany the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining of the Said Book; when the Time was Come for it. Which is an Indiſputable Reſult from the Two next-foregoing Theorems. (X.) The Preciſe Time for the Fulfilling of <hi>Rev.</hi> v. 5. is That, wherein the <hi>Firſt</hi> No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice was to be giv'n, of the <hi>True</hi> Way of Expounding the Book.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:34828:3"/>For when upon Loud Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made, No One in All the World was Found Able to Do it, to the Great Grief of ſuch as Earneſtly Deſir'd it, <hi>Weep not,</hi> (ſa<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s one of the Elders;) <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, the Lion of the Tribe of</hi> Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da, &amp;c. <hi>hath Prevail'd to Op'n the Book;</hi> that is, He hath O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p'n'd it by Mee. For if he meant Only, That Chriſt Could Do it, if he Would; it is <hi>Gratis Dictum.</hi> And one might as well ſay, of the hitherto-Unintelligible Parts of <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> That Chriſt hath Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail'd to Op'n Them too. But we are ne'er the Wiſer for it Yet. The Elder's Meaning there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt be This; Behold, <hi>The Lion of the Tribe of</hi> Juda, &amp;c. hath Inſtructed ME to Op'n the Book, and Looſe its Seals. (XI.) Mr. <hi>MEDE</hi> is the Pers'n, that gave the Firſt Notice of the Book's Op'ning, <hi>Anno.</hi> 1632. and made a very Conſiderable Progreſs in it. And is Conſequently That <hi>Elder</hi> Spok'n of <hi>Rev.</hi> v. 5. For This, we have the Teſtimony of Monſ. <hi>Jurieu, Accomp. of Scrip. Proph. Part.</hi> I. <hi>Chap.</hi> VIII. Joſeph Mede, <hi>in my Opinion, is the Firſt that <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtood Any thing of the Sealed Book.</hi> We have alſo the Concurrent Evidence of All Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Interpreters (excepting <hi>H. Grotius,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Hammond,</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted by All Proteſtants, and Rejected ev'n by <hi>Monſieur de Meaux</hi> Himſelf, in his <hi>Explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Apocalyps, Pref. pag.</hi> 62.) that have Joyn'd their Suffrage with him. But This Propoſition can be No Otherwiſe Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated, than by Aſwering Any Man's Objections, that Diſſents from us, which he will find E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>now, that will be Ready to En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage in. But Thus much is Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, That, (if Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> be not the <hi>Firſt;</hi>) Whoever Is, or ſhall be the <hi>Firſt,</hi> is the <hi>Elder</hi> There Mentioned; I Mean in <hi>Rev.</hi> v. 5. And Conſequently, of the Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the 24 <hi>Elders, Rev.</hi> iv. 4. And the Church, he is a Member of, is That, whoſe Eſtabliſhment is Predicted, <hi>Rev.</hi> iv. (XII.) Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Reformation No Man Underſtood the Book. This is So Apparent; that the Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is not, I believe, ſo much as Pretended by Any Man what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever. (XIII.) The Sealed Book therefore, whoſe Op'ning is Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figur'd, <hi>Rev.</hi> v. Said to be <hi>Writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t'n Within, and on the Back-ſide,</hi> is a Book in the Form We Now have them; and Not, in a ROLL; as Books were Wont to be Made-up in S. <hi>John</hi>'s time. Of which Book, the Outſide-writing is the Text; as it lies before Us in Theſe Days; and is Read by E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Child at School, as ſoon as he can Speak. But the Senſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained Under That, is the Inſide-writing; which is Found Only in the Skilful Interpreter. The Seal is the Myſterious Expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And whereas the Whole Book is indeed but One Continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:34828:3"/>Myſtery All along; the Holy Spirit, by Dividing it, (as his Uſual Manner is) into Sev'n Parts, makes, as it were, Sev'n Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of it; which He Calls, (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Uſe of Scripture in Such Caſes,) <hi>Seven Seals.</hi> This I Obſerve, with reſpect to the Learned, and Ingenious, but yet Needleſs, Fancy, of thoſe, who have tak'n the Pains to Excogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate a Way, How a Roll might be Seal'd with Sev'n Seals, ſo that the Op'ning of the Firſt, might not at the Same Time Diſcloſe the Viſion of the Second. As if, at the Time, when the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion was to be Explain'd, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion for Books, was to be in Rolls. (XIV.) The <hi>Lamb Revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved after Slaughter, Standing in the midſt of the Throne;</hi> who <hi>Came, and Took the Book, out of the Hand of the Sitter on the Throne, Chap.</hi> v. 6, 7. Cannot be Chriſt in Pers'n, who Comes not to Any Earthly Throne, (as the Throne we Speak of is;) but it is Chriſt, in Some Good King, who was to be Slain, as was his Maſter; and to Riſe again in a Figure, (as <hi>Iſaac</hi> is ſaid to have Done, <hi>Heb.</hi> xi. 19.) and as our Good King <hi>Charles</hi> the Martyr Did, in his Son of the Same name; when he was reſtor'd, as it were to Life again, <hi>Anno,</hi> 1660. Such kind a of Reſurrection, is No Stranger to the Prophets; for which ſee <hi>Ezek.</hi> xxxvii. 11.-14. <hi>Rom.</hi> xi. 15. Now Whoever <hi>Firſt</hi> was to Op'n the Book, his Performance was to be Seconded with ſuch a Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, <hi>Rev.</hi> v. 5.6. Which, as it Never Happen'd in the World Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; So we may Hope, that there will Never be Occaſion for Such Another. And if there ſhould Not, the Book muſt have been Op<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n'd <hi>Before</hi> the Reſtauration of King <hi>Charles</hi> The Second. (XV<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.) Alſo, Before the Op'ning of the Book, there was to be a Loud Proclamation, by a <hi>Strong</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Mighty, or Powerful) <hi>Angel,</hi> for Any one to come and Op'n the Book, that Could. Which, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Mr. <hi>Mede</hi>'s Op'ning it, was made by King <hi>James</hi> I. Accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as I have Shew'd at large, in my Expoſition of Chap. v. All which things, with a Great Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny More, Conſpire to Fix the Honour, of Shewing the Way to Op'n It, upon Mr. <hi>Mede;</hi> and Conſequently, That, of being the Church Prefigur'd in <hi>Rev.</hi> iv, and v. upon This Church of Ours. For indeed (to Sum-up All in ſhort) upon This Hypotheſis, not only the Expoſition of the ſaid Two Chapters; but alſo, of the Three Foregoing ones, and of Every Particular in them, Runs Strangely Smooth, and Natural, and Ev'ry way Unexceptionable; as I have made Appear, by a Thorow-Expoſition, I have Publiſh'd, of them. Which, if the <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> had been Wrong, would have
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:34828:4"/>been As Impoſſible at leaſt, for Me to have done; as it has been for All Other Interpreters, (Men of as Great Learning, Wit, and Fancy, as the World afford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,) who have Proceeded on a Wrong <hi>Hypotheſis.</hi> But inſtead of That, I have Shewn the Sev'n Epiſtles, and the Fourth and Fifth Chapters, to be a Prophecy of the Church, from the Beginning, to the Times We live in, by Such a Clear, and Solid Expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, of Ev'ry Type and Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage in them, as may Defie All Oppoſition; and which Cannot Reas'nably be Aſcrib'd, to Any thing but its TRUTH.</p>
            <p>The Only <hi>Objections,</hi> worth the Mentioning, that are come to My Knowledge, are Theſe. <hi>Obj.</hi> 1. We have No Nocturnal Service; and therefore cannot be ſaid, <hi>not</hi> to <hi>Reſt Day and Night, Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Holy, H, H;</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. We account, as from Midnight to Noon, Morning: So from Noon to Midnight again, Night. Thus, at Any Time After Noon, we are Taught to Pray, <hi>Light'n our Darkneſs,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and Defend us from All Perils and Dangers of This NIGHT. Anſ.</hi> 2. By <hi>Day and Night</hi> (as by <hi>Ev'ning and Morning, Gen.</hi> i. 5, 8, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) <hi>in ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu Conjuncto,</hi> by a <hi>Hendiadis,</hi> may be Meant a Natural Day of 24 Hours; Call'd alſo <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> xi. 25. And ſo the Senſe will be, That Every 24 Hours, (or Every Day,) they Fail not Oft'n to Rehearſe the ſaid Hymn.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> 2. Neither is <hi>England</hi> Large enough, nor the Pers'ns, I mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as Concern'd in the Prophecy, of Eminent Regard enough (for Grandeur, Fame, or Piety,) for the Spirit to Intend in This Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable Viſion. <hi>Anſ.</hi> Then Ought it to be ſhown, That I have ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Miſinterpreted, or Miſappli'd the Words, or ſome Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Part of them. For if, With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Either of Theſe Faults, the Words be Granted to be Well A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dapted to a People, that was not Intended by the Author; Whoſe Honour, pray, will That Reflect upon? Such Objections therefore as Theſe, that have No Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the Prophecy, are Mere Prejudices. For, Why is not the Church of <hi>England</hi> Large e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough? Only becauſe we Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy ſo. For, Where does the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy Require, either a More Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſive Church, than This of <hi>England,</hi> to be Fulfill'd in? Or, more Eminent and Renowned Pers'ns (in their ſeveral Stations) than were Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> King <hi>James</hi> I. King <hi>Charles</hi> I. and II. and (for an <hi>Elder</hi>) than <hi>Joſeph Mede?</hi> But Particularly, as for King <hi>Charles</hi> II. it is Plain, that He had Piety Enough, to Anſwer All His Part in the Prediction, to the Full; and with That, let Every one, that pretends to Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>s'n, Reſt Satisfi'd. For it cannot be Deni'd, but that King <hi>Charles</hi> II.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:34828:4"/>with All his Faults, was, in the Hands of CHRIST, a Noble Inſtrument of our Political RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DEMPTION. And if we think his Private Converſation to have been hardly Suitable to That High Character; yet ſince, at the Same Time, we Cannot but Confeſs the Prophecy to be Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſht in him; give me leave to Remember you, That God ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, in the Unſearchable Depths of his Wiſdom and Juſtice, is Found to have made, of the Chief Stones in his Edifice, <hi>Stones of Stumbling;</hi> at which however, it Becomes not Us (nay, it is very Dangerons for us) to he Offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. From which Danger we can only be Secure, in Taking our Meaſures from the Word of God; and Not from our Own Delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Fancies and Prej<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dices. And, May Our New <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> in This, take Warning by the Old one. For it is grown too Plauſible and Popular a Humour (becauſe ſo well Attemper'd to Moſt Mens Capacities, or Deſigns) to Vilifie Prophetic Speculations, upon Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected Ignorances, and Miſappre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. Wherein we are not a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Uncharitable, upon many Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts. But Eſpecially, in reſpect of Thoſe, who Otherwiſe might be Converted by them, from the Error of their ways. As, in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, in reſpect of Non-Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts, and Separatiſts; to whom it would be a Singular Piece of Service, to have it Made-out Clearly to them, That the Church of <hi>England,</hi> By Law Eſtabliſht, is the Church Predicted of in the Fourth and Fifth Chapters of the Revelation: That they Periſh not in their Dividing Practices, and Unchriſtian Strifes, and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulations. For Our Sectaries do More than cry, <hi>I am of</hi> Paul, <hi>and I of</hi> Apollos, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And yet ev'n That, is by the Apoſtle Term'd <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Diviſion, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, Faction; Envying,</hi> or <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation, Strife, Contention,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> i. 11, 12. iii. 3, 4. and Said to be (in its Own Nature) Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, <hi>Gal.</hi> v. 20, 21. According<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Same Apoſtle lays a Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious Curſe upon Such Make<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> xvi. 22. <hi>If Any Man Love not the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, let him be Anathema, Maran-atha.</hi> For he had moſt Earneſtly Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſought them, Chap. i. 10. <hi>BY THE NAME OF O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R LORD JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST, to Speak All the Same Thing; and that there be No Diviſions among them; but Perfect Concord, in the Same Mind, and in the Same Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> With reſpect to which, in the end of the Same Epiſtle, (as is ſaid Already) he, in his Zeal for the Churches Unity, does Solemnly Denounce <hi>Anathema, Maran-atha,</hi> upon all Thoſe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>s'ns, with whom, for want of <hi>LOVE</hi> to the <hi>LORD JE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST,</hi> his Obteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhould prove Ineffectual.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:34828:5"/>
            <p> I am not therefore of Their Mind, who give-out, That the Fomenters of Unreas'nable Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions, may be Sav'd: Ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves upon 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> iii. 12,-15. For the Apoſtle does not ſay, (as They Imagin,) That the Builders of Ill DOCTRINS ſhall be Sav'd; but, of III Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>s'ns. For the Building he is There Treating of, are <hi>Pers'ns.</hi> He Explains himſelf ſo, Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ver. 9. <hi>YE are God's Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry: YE</hi> (Pers'ns, Not Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines.) <hi>are God's Building.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeably in the Next Verſes, <hi>CHRIST</hi> (ſays he) <hi>is the Foundation.</hi> The Foundation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, wee ſee, and Whole Stru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, are not Doctrines, but Pers'ns. Whereof Some are <hi>Gold,</hi> and Some <hi>Stubble.</hi> But tho' the Stubble be Burnt, yet the Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſhall be Sav'd; if he were not in Fault. But This, in Building of Dividing Errors, (which is indeed, Deſtroying, or Pulling-Down, and Not, Building,) Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not Rightly be Affirm'd. I am Sure S. <hi>Paul,</hi> in That Place, is very Far from So Saying. Be Zealous therefore, Brethren, and Repent; and Joyn your ſelves, with All Alacrity, to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of That Heav'nly Church, which, in the Fourth and Fifth Chapters of the Revelation (and I might Add, the Tenth, and Many More, as will Appear Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after,) is Adorn'd and Honour'd with So Glorious a Teſtimony from the Spirit of Prophecy.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Ev'n ſuch as will not Believe without a Sign from Heaven, might hence Receive In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible Satisfaction. For the Revelation, Set in its True Light, (as Now it is,) What is it but A STANDING SIGN from Heav'n, A PERMA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NENT and PERPETU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>AL MIRACLE? For therein is Our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the Lord of Glory, Conſpicuouſly Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal'd from Heav'n, for Sixteen Hundred Years ago, to have ſet in Order, the Grand Affairs, and Revolutions, of the moſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Parts of His Empire in the World; from its Beginning, to our Own Times, Incluſively. Which Conſider'd, with What Conſcience can any Man Deny the Being, or the Providence of God? or, that the Scriptures are his Genuine Oracles? (among which he finds the <hi>Revelation,</hi> to be So (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,) <hi>Self-Evident,</hi> and to Carry the Authority of the Others, Shining in it;) or Call in Queſtion Any Point, or Article (Eſpecially of the Prime, and Fundamental ones) of Our Religion? For it is not Poſſible to be Objected againſt the <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation,</hi> (as was of Old, by <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyry,</hi> againſt Part of <hi>Daniel</hi>'s Prophecy,) That it was Compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed After the Things were Done. <hi>Hieron. Praef. Com. in Dan.</hi> And yet it is as Plainly, and as Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Accompliſht, as if it had been So Indeed; or, as if the Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:34828:5"/>of More than 1600 Years, had All been Writt'n Purpoſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in Favour of a Prophecy but <hi>Newly <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtood;</hi> and yet in Every bodies <hi>Hands</hi> So Long <hi>Before.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And Can we make a Trivial Matter, Sirs, of Such Diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries? Which are, in True Eſteem, the Glory of Chriſtianity; and which, if Duly Cultivated, and Improv'd, (as they both Might, and Ought to be,) would Equal the Condition of Our Times, to That of the Firſt Ages of the Church; as to the Certainty, that we might Gain Thereby, of our Religion; and the Proof, they would enable us to Make of it. And let No Man Here Cry-out upon the Strength of Imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; till he has Well Weigh'd the Aſſertion, and Knows himſelf Able to Confute it. For, How Eaſily are the Miſts of Fancy, Diſpell'd by the Light, and Warmth of Sound Reas'n? For My Part, I am very Senſible <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> (I Bleſs God for it) That the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the Spirit, has So Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triv'd the Texture of This Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy, that a Foreign Expoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it may as Eaſily be Blown away, as a Looſe Feather. A Lock, with ſo Many Subſtantial Wards to it, is not to be Pickt. Which is the True Cauſe, that not One of the Admirers of <hi>H. Gr.</hi> or Dr. <hi>Hammond,</hi> has at Any time Appear'd, in Vindication of Their Expoſitions; they are ſo Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly, and ſo Groſly Faulty. And ſo All Others Needs muſt be, that Err, (as They do) in the Main Subject of the Viſion. For a Concluſion therefore of this Paper, I Heartily Commend it, to the Good Bleſſing of the Great God our Saviour; To Whom be All Glory for Ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed and are to be Sold by the Bookſellers of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
